<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Technology | mlindgren.ca]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/categories/technology/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-12T20:32:54-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.mlindgren.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mitch Lindgren]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Switching to Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2012/09/23/switching-to-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-23T23:22:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2012/09/23/switching-to-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been using Wordpress on various sites that I&rsquo;ve maintained for probably the
better part of a decade now. By most metrics, it&rsquo;s still very good blogging
software; I&rsquo;m not aware of any self-hostable alternative that can match
Wordpress in terms of the union of ease of use, feature set and flexibility that
it provides. That said, lately I&rsquo;ve been feeling that perhaps Wordpress is no
longer the right choice for my specific needs. These are my problems with it:</p>

<ul>
<li>It&rsquo;s not very good for sharing source code. There are a multitude of plugins
available for syntax highlighting; the best of them seems to be
<a href="http://alexgorbatchev.com/SyntaxHighlighter/">Alex Gorbatchev&rsquo;s Syntax Highlighter</a>,
which is used by
<a href="http://wordpress.com">Wordpress.com</a> and is also what I was using on my blog.
But I&rsquo;ve had problems with the Wordpress converting some of the characters in
my code to HTML entities (e.g. <code>&amp;amp;</code> for &amp; ) which are then printed
literally by the plugin.</li>
<li>I find that more often than not Wordpress' visual editor is
insufficient for the formatting I want in my posts. That forces me to use
the raw HTML editor. That would be fine, except that Wordpress has a strange
sort of off-spec way of storing post HTML. Paragraph and line break tags are
omitted in the editor and the database, and are added when the page is
actually rendered to the client. This is okay, I guess, and I <em>think</em>
Wordpress is smart enough to not insert extra paragraph tags if you do wrap
your own paragraphs with them. Still, it leads to some unpredictability with
regard to how a post with hand-written HTML will actually be rendered.</li>
<li>A similar but worse problem occurs when you try to insert extra line breaks.
Even if you&rsquo;re using the raw HTML editor to insert <code>&lt;br /&gt;</code> tags, Wordpress
will just get rid of them unless you insert additional non-breaking spaces
(<code>&amp;nbsp;</code>) so that it thinks the lines are non-empty. But! If you switch back
to the visual editor for any reason, even your <code>&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;</code> lines will be
wiped out. Even for &ldquo;average&rdquo; users I can&rsquo;t think of any situation in which
this &ldquo;feature&rdquo; would be desirable. If I put a bunch of extra newlines into
something I&rsquo;m writing, it is because <em>I want exactly that many newlines.</em> I
tend to not have much patience for software that thinks it&rsquo;s smarter than
I am; that is why I still write most of my code in <a href="http://www.vim.org/">Vim</a>
and use hand-written makefiles in an age of
<acronym title="Integrated Development Environment">IDE</acronym>s.</li>
<li>Never-ending updates. It seems like every time I log in there&rsquo;s a new update
to download. Wordpress has updates down to a one-click install process, so
this wouldn&rsquo;t be much of a problem except for the fact that
every time I have to update Wordpress warns me that I should back up my
database first. Why? Is there a significant possibility that the update might
break everything? It&rsquo;s probably just a
<acronym title="Cover Our Asses">COA</acronym>, and I back up my database
daily anyway, but this whole aspect of Wordpress makes me uneasy and I don&rsquo;t
want to have to deal with it any more. Even though I&rsquo;m covered for backups,
recovering from a botched update would undoubtedly be a nightmare.</li>
<li><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WordPress#Vulnerabilities">Vulnerabilities.</a> One
of the big reasons that Wordpress is updated so frequently is that it has a
long history of security vulnerabilities, and more are still being discovered
and patched. This also means that if I don&rsquo;t log in frequently enough to
download new security patches, I&rsquo;m at risk of having my site compromised,
loaded up with malware and blacklisted by Google.</li>
<li><p>It&rsquo;s written in PHP. <a href="http://me.veekun.com/blog/2012/04/09/php-a-fractal-of-bad-design/">PHP sucks.</a>
(I can&rsquo;t link to that enough.) I don&rsquo;t want to be dogmatic about technology
choices; good software is good software regardless of what language it&rsquo;s
written in, and my primary desire is always to use whatever is best for the
task at hand. But lately I&rsquo;ve been pretty vocal, both here and in person with
friends and colleagues, about how bad PHP is. Continuing to rely on it
undermines my credibility on the issue and makes me a bit of a hypocrite.</p>

<p>And while this might seem trivial or pedantic, it&rsquo;s
actually one of the root causes of almost all of the issues above; the weird
HTML handling, inappropriate entity conversion, and security issues are all
due, at least in part, to bad design patterns popularized and perpetuated by
PHP. Wordpress still uses raw non-parameterized SQL queries; blogging software
built on a modern web framework with a proper
<acronym title="Object-Relational Mapping">ORM</acronym>
would not be plagued by SQL
injection exploits as Wordpress has been historically and probably continues
to be.</p></li>
<li>Wordpress supports themes so that you can customize the apperance of your
site, but editing them kind of sucks, because they&rsquo;re all written in PHP
instead of a proper templating language. Years ago I actually wrote a lot of
PHP, but I still find Wordpress templates pretty ugly and difficult to
understand; they seem more verbose than should really be necessary for what
they accomplish, and have, on average, more <code>&lt;?php ?&gt;</code> sections than a
keyboard has keys. (That analogy sucked. Sorry, it&rsquo;s late. What I&rsquo;m trying to
say is that there are a lot of them.)</li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<p>So recently I got it into my head to switch over to
<a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress.</a> Octopress bills itself as &ldquo;a blogging
framework for hackers,&rdquo; which is an attractive description given my
<a href="/categories/coding">predilections.</a> It uses
<a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</a> to generate static pages from a set
of templates and content written in
<a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">Markdown.</a><sup>1</sup> It is,
without a doubt, harder to use than to Wordpress, but it has the following
advantages:</p>

<ul>
<li>Rendering static pages once and serving dynamic content via AJAX is much more
efficient than rendering entire pages dynamically for each visitor. This isn&rsquo;t
really a concern for me because this is a very low-traffic site, and I have an
entire quad-core <acronym title="Virtual Private Server">VPS</acronym>
doing basically nothing besides serving this site. That said, it&rsquo;s nice to
know that when I start doing other stuff on my VPS, I won&rsquo;t be contending for
cycles with PHP and MySQL, so the site will always be very responsive. Plus,
wow does the site load fast now (once you have that huge header image cached,
anyway. I&rsquo;ll fix that soon.) Also not a huge concern for a blog, but I
didn&rsquo;t expect the difference to even be noticeable, and it definitely is.</li>
<li>Static pages significantly decrease the attack surface of the site; there is
no database, so no SQL injection to worry about, and no scripts are being
executed, so <a href="http://www.kb.cert.org/vuls/id/520827">PHP vulnerabilities</a>
aren&rsquo;t a concern.</li>
<li>Static pages means I get a nicely organized, easily navigable directory
structure instead of God-awful rewrite rules.</li>
<li>The default Octopress theme is very well designed and well-suited to
customization.  I was able to modify it to make it look almost exactly like my
old custom Wordpress theme did, while retaining the fully fluid layout of the
Octopress theme&mdash;meaning that the layout will resize to look beautiful at
any screen resolution, including on mobile devices.</li>
<li>Octopress has pretty nice built in Github and Twitter widgets.</li>
<li>Comments are handled by <a href="http://disqus.com/">Disqus</a>, which provides a nicer
comment system than Wordpress' built in comments.  I was using Disqus anyway
via a plugin, but now I don&rsquo;t have to worry about keeping the Disqus comments
synced with the Wordpress database. Incidentally, Disqus provides a very nice
system to migrate comments to new URLs by uploading a
<acronym title="Comma Separate Value">CSV</acronym> file mapping old URLs to
new URLs. They&rsquo;ve really thought of everything, so props to them for providing
a great service.</li>
<li>All of the blog content is stored on my local machine, which means I can write
posts in a disconnected environment using Vim, version control them with Git,
and then push them to my server when they&rsquo;re finished. I have a nice
deployment setup where everything is stored in a Git repository on the server
and a post-commit hook copies the updated content to the web root for the blog
subdomain. All I have to do is <code>git push</code> and the blog is instantly updated.</li>
<li>Since Wordpress uses hand-written SQL queries, it is tightly coupled with
MySQL and doesn&rsquo;t support any other database. PHP is similarly tied to Apache;
while it&rsquo;s possible to run it with other servers, it&rsquo;s not particularly easy.
By ditching Wordpress, I can also get rid of Apache, PHP and MySQL. This is
nice since I was planning to use nginx and Postgres for my
<a href="/entry/2012/09/14/social-networks-and-content-ownership/">photo album project</a>
anyway.</li>
</ul>


<p>Those are, give or take a few minor considerations, my reasons for switching
blogging platforms. I&rsquo;d be remiss to not mention that Octopress does have some
noteworthy disadvantages even for &ldquo;power users&rdquo; to whom the above advantages
might sound attractive.
<a href="http://alblue.bandlem.com/2012/02/disadvantages-of-octopress.html" title="Disadvantages of Octopress - AlBlue's Blog">This post</a>
does a good job cataloguing a few of them. On the balance, though, I feel like
it&rsquo;s a good choice for me, and although the switch took me considerably longer
than I expected (the better part of an weekend where I&rsquo;d expected an evening or
so of work), I&rsquo;m pretty happy that I did it.</p>

<p>In an upcoming post, I&rsquo;ll discuss the actual process of reconfiguring my server
and importing all of my content (which is what I had planned to do before this
turned into a 1,600 word diatribe against Wordpress.) For now, if I&rsquo;ve inspired
you and you&rsquo;re thinking about switching your own Wordpress site to Octopress,
you can take a look at the
<a href="https://github.com/mlindgren/wp2octopress"><acronym title="Extract, Transform, Load">ETL</acronym> I wrote</a>
to ease the import process.</p>

<p><sup>1</sup> <small>Did you know that Markdown was created by John Gruber? Until very
recently, I didn&rsquo;t. And here I thought all he did was play apologist for
Apple.</small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Social networks and content ownership]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2012/09/14/social-networks-and-content-ownership/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-14T00:45:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2012/09/14/social-networks-and-content-ownership</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m always wary about pre-announcing things I&rsquo;m working on; I have more ambition than spare time, which leads to a tendency to start projects and not finish them.  But if there&rsquo;s to be a point in maintaining this website, I need to actually <em>write things</em> once in a while, so I may as well write about what I&rsquo;ve been hacking on lately.  At the moment, I&rsquo;m building a web-based photo album in Python.  My primary reason for doing this is that I&rsquo;d like to own more of my information.  Apps and social networks have some significant advantages, particularly for the less technologically inclined, but I&rsquo;m ambivalent about the trend away from an open Internet and towards a set of non-interoperable, monolithic walled-garden services.<!-- more --></p>

<p>When Google+ debuted, my enthusiasm for the service followed a sort of bell curve.  I was already using Twitter and Facebook, and I didn&rsquo;t want to have to post everything to yet another service.  At the urging of friends, I joined anyway, and warmed to it considerably.  It was simply better software than Facebook; the interface was cleaner, the privacy controls more usable, the communication options more diverse, the means of sharing and interacting with media more engaging and deeply integrated.  Best of all, there wasn&rsquo;t nearly as much app spam.  Much of this is probably still true, although the impression I get from Google+ pages I&rsquo;ve stumbled across recently is that they&rsquo;ve been trying to make it look more like Facebook, to its detriment.</p>

<p>Realizing that it was a better product in almost every regard, I started using Google+ almost exclusively and tried to recruit additional friends away from Facebook.  I stopped uploading new photos to Facebook and even purchased additional storage capacity on Google+ so I could upload all of my photos there at the original quality.  Problems quickly became apparent, though.  Despite my best efforts, nobody was using the service; even among those of my friends who were enthusiastic early adopters, actual <em>social</em> activity among my circles dropped off quickly, and I soon found myself wondering why I even bothered to check for updates.  I finally deleted my account when I logged in one day and realized that the newest post in my news feed was from several months prior.</p>

<p>And with my Google+ account, there went all of the photos and other content I had uploaded.  I still have the files, of course, but the effort I expended in selecting a handful of good photos to upload to each gallery from the hundreds of shots I take on most outings, not to mention the comments, captions, and other metadata I had curated, vanished into the ether with not a trace left behind.  The moral of the story is that private social networks are impermanent, and thus anything uploaded to them necessarily has an unknown but very much finite period of accessibility and relevance.  Whether or not Google ever admits it, Google+ never quite took off, but it could have supplanted Facebook just as Facebook did MySpace.  If and when some other service comes along and succeeds where Google+ failed, every user on Facebook will be forced to start over from scratch on whatever&rsquo;s in vogue next.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m tired of playing that game. I want to keep control over the content I create so that I can truly decide how it&rsquo;s shared and with whom, and so that if I need to migrate my data to a new system, I have the means to do so.<sup>1</sup> The ultimate realization of this ideal is in decentralized services based on open protocols, such as <a title="Tent" href="http://tent.io/">Tent</a>. I&rsquo;m very enthusiastic about such attempts, but realistically, I&rsquo;m skeptical that any of them will ever gain the necessary traction to make a real difference. Even if Tent or some analogue gains millions of users, it will be a drop in the bucket compared to Facebook, and entrenched players such as Facebook will have no incentive to interoperate because decentralized services do nothing but threaten their business model.</p>

<p>I will do as much as is in my power to help services like Tent succeed, but for the time being, that is not much.  That kind of leaves me without a good means of pushing my content to the people who care about it.  Nevertheless, I can still take ownership of it by hosting it on my own server using my own tools.  That is the purpose of developing my own photo album software.  I&rsquo;m making good progress so far, and hopefully soon I&rsquo;ll have more to share; once the code is in a reasonably complete state with most of the major features I want for my own purposes, I intend to make the app open source and share the code on my <a title="mlindgren on Github" href="https://github.com/mlindgren" target="_blank">Github account.</a>  And now that I&rsquo;ve announced my intent publicly, I expect anyone who reads this to hold me to my plan to ensure that I get it finished!</p>

<p><sup>1</sup> <small>Both Facebook and Google+ provide a means of exporting the data you&rsquo;ve shared. I believe both will export everything belonging to you personally, but I don&rsquo;t think you necessarily get to keep all of the social data associated with your content, e.g. comments, nor the relationships between different pieces of content. Last I checked, the data was merely dumped into a bunch of flat files; nothing is kept in a structured format that makes it easy to work with, and even if it were, other privates services don&rsquo;t usually offer the option to import your data. While it may still not be easy, if you own your own data and manage it using open source tools, it&rsquo;s at least <em>possible</em> to migrate everything to another system with the greatest fidelity supported by that system.</small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to reinstall OS X from a disc image using only one computer]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2011/09/21/how-to-reinstall-os-x-from-a-disc-image-using-only-one-computer/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-21T00:17:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2011/09/21/how-to-reinstall-os-x-from-a-disc-image-using-only-one-computer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My internship recently ended, and as such, I had to move from Calgary back to Edmonton, where I&rsquo;ll be completing the fourth year of my Computing Science degree at the University of Alberta. I hope to be able to write more about my internship later, but at the moment I want to share a handy trick I discovered for reinstalling OS X. The reason I bring up the move is that after I arrived in Edmonton, I found myself wanting to reformat my Mac Mini and re-install Snow Leopard, but my Snow Leopard disc was nowhere to be found. Luckily, as a semi-paranoid computer scientist with an abundance of disk space, I keep images of important discs on my network-attached storage device for just such occasions.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, however, the Snow Leopard disc image is large enough that it can only be burned to a dual-layer DVD. I don&rsquo;t tend to keep writeable dual-layer DVDs lying around, so I needed a solution which required only the disc image itself. There are a number of methods available for installing OS X over the network, but none of them seemed to work for me—perhaps owing to the fact that I had only one Mac. Luckily, I discovered that you can install OS X from a separate partition on the same disk. Here&rsquo;s how:</p>

<ol>
    <li>First, you'll need to re-partition your disk. Open Disk Utility and select the disk you want to use. Be sure to select the disk itself, rather than one of its partitions, which are indented beneath the disk.</li>
    <li>Click the + button to add a new partition, and drag the new partition's section in the disk layout graph upwards until it's large enough to store your operating system disc image. Apply the changes. It may take some time for the disk to be re-partitioned.</li>
    <li>Now, select the new partition from the list on the left. Go to the Restore tab, and restore your operating system disc image to the new partition.</li>
    <li>Once the restore is complete, restart your computer, holding Option (Alt) at start-up. This should bring up a list of available start-up disks. Choose your new partition.</li>
    <li>You should now be at the installer, and you can re-install to your primary partition. Once the installation is complete, delete your installation disc partition to and resize the primary partition to reclaim the extra space.</li>
</ol>


<p>That&rsquo;s it! In retrospect, it&rsquo;s completely obvious, but I haven&rsquo;t seen these instructions anywhere else on the web. This technique might be particularly useful for owners of Macs without disc drives.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I'm considering switching back to iOS. Here's why.]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2011/06/12/im-considering-switching-back-to-ios-heres-why/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-12T22:13:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2011/06/12/im-considering-switching-back-to-ios-heres-why</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>In September of last year I ditched my iPhone 3G and switched to the Android-powered HTC Desire (which I later sold in order to purchase a Desire Z, which sports a physical keyboard.)  I'm sad to report that I'm now considering switching back to iOS, after less than a year on the Android platform.  The following is an excerpt from an e-mail I wrote to a friend of mine whom I'd describe as a fervent Android evangelist, detailing some of the frustrations I have with the operating system and why I feel that I might be better served by iOS.  I've edited it slightly to make it more readable for anyone who might come across this blog.</em></p>




<p><em>I really want to like the Android platform, and writing this gave me no joy.  There are two reasons I'm posting it here, though.  The first is simply that the purpose of this website is for me to post about my programming and my experiences with technology (as well as whatever else catches my fancy.)  The second is that I hope that sharing my honest opinion about Android might be helpful to anyone considering a phone purchase.</em></p>


<!-- more -->




<p>As mentioned on Twitter, my number one complaint is having to use custom ROMs.  <em>There are always problems</em> with custom ROMs.  <a href="http://www.cyanogenmod.com/">CyanogenMod 7</a> caused my phone to reboot at random.  I also had problems with the Contacts app crashing.  All of these issues persisted throughout multiple versions of CM7 up to and including final.</p>




<ul>
    <li>With the ROM I'm using now (a custom Sense ROM, can't remember the exact name), I can't set the SSID/password on my WiFi hotspot because Settings crashes when I try to.  I seriously haven't used a single custom ROM that hasn't had some issues with it.</li>
    <li>You mentioned that Google is promising quicker updates, but I'll believe it when I see it.  Are they actually forcing manufacturers to do this in order to use Android branding or get Google apps, or are they just asking nicely?  The latter won't work.  And as far as I know, all that the Android update committee has promised is 18 months of updates following the launch of a new device.  So does that mean if I release a device and then push a point release to consumers 17 months later, I've fulfilled that? All I see here is flowery language, and frankly I don't think anything is going to improve.<br /><br />

The fact is that it's not profitable for these manufacturers to update existing devices when they could spend the same development effort on releasing another six phones, so unless Google does something to change that, nothing will happen.</li>
</ul>




<p>The rest are in no particular order:</p>




<ul>
    <li>No good Exchange client available.  Even Touchdown, which is expensive, is pretty bad.  The HTC client is okay, but it <del datetime="2011-06-12T02:36:52+00:00">doesn't support important features like threading.</del> [I later realized that this is untrue; the HTC client does support threading.  I still find it cumbersome to use, and I've previously had problems with it failing to send messages without any notification of the failure.  That's a pretty big problem when you're using it for work e-mail.]</li>
    <li>Launcher redraw, agghhhhhh.  Sense is horrendous for this, but I much prefer the built-in Sense apps to their Google alternatives, so I feel like I'm stuck using it.  Even on stock Android, it seems like I can't really use live wallpapers or I have to wait for the launcher to reload all the time.</li>
    <li>It's annoying that when I read an e-mail in Gmail on my computer, the notification for it stays in my notification bar.  Also, my Gmail push seems to have stopped working of late.  To be fair, it remains to be seen how the new iPhone notification system handles these things.</li>
    <li>I've noticed that with multiple IM clients (specifically, AIM and eBuddy) if I leave them running in the background while I'm doing other things like browsing the Internet, I'll eventually get signed out or the app will close.  I don't know if this is just because they're not written correctly, but it's annoying; IM is the only thing I really use background applications for and it doesn't seem to work consistently.</li>
    <li>I often have trouble sending/receiving MMS.  It's frustrating when someone sends me an MMS and I have to ask them to e-mail it to me instead because it won't download.</li>
    <li>Camera quality on the Desire Z is pretty bad.  I'm certain the iPhone 4 is better in this department.  I feel like my Desire Z's camera is actually worse than my Desire's camera for still photos (although it's better for video.)  This isn't a strike against Android in particular, but the problem of lower-quality hardware is endemic to the platform in a certain sense.</li>
    <li>A lot of apps in the Android market are just very poor quality. The iPhone app store has its fair share of bad apps, but I still feel like the average quality is much higher there.  In particular, any app that's available for both platforms is almost always better on iPhone.  A prime example is Facebook.  The Android client was horribly broken for several weeks, and regardless of that, it just doesn't support the same feature set as the iPhone version (e.g. watching videos.)</li>
    <li>I complained about this even before I bought an Android phone, but the Android operating system is sometimes just not very responsive.  Scrolling is sometimes smooth, but rarely as smooth as on iPhone/Windows Phone 7.  Minor annoyance, but an annoyance nonetheless.</li>
    <li>I'm not sure if you're familiar with the life cycle of an app in Android, but basically every different screen you can go to in an app is a separate "activity"&mdash;essentially a separate application.  <em>What were they thinking</em> in designing it like this? It causes so many problems.  Any time the "state" of the phone changes (e.g. you rotate the device, the phone leaves/enters roaming, etc.) the activity is destroyed and re-created unless developers manually override this behavior.  This is why, for instance, the keyboard often disappears if you have it open and then rotate the phone.  (Highly polished apps like Twitter handle rotation properly, but don't be fooled; it's not the default behavior.  Many other apps do not handle rotation very well.)  Other examples of activity recreation problems include pop-up dialog boxes disappearing and fields losing focus.</li>
    <li>Editing text sucks; I find that my phone never seems to do what I want it to when I'm trying to highlight or copy and paste some text.</li>
    <li>I've had problems on both of my Android phones with the music player pausing in the middle of a song at random.  This has happened in multiple different media players.  It's as though the phone thinks the headphones are being removed when they are in fact still in place.</li>
    <li>I like being able to set alarm/ringer/media volume separately (although the iPhone can also do this), but I don't like that the defaults on Android aren't very sensible.  For instance, if I have my ringer silenced, it probably means that I also want my media silenced.  But that's not what happens if I just use the volume button; I have to actually go into settings and change the media volume separately.</li>
    <li>Sometimes Google Talk just flat out refuses to start for me until I reboot my phone.  This happened on multiple ROMs.  On the Desire I noticed that it seemed to refuse to start when I was low on internal storage.  I'm not sure why it does it on my Desire Z.  This should be a core platform feature on par with BBM, but it seems to be very poorly supported.</li>
    <li>From a developer perspective, I hate paying a development fee to Apple to be able to install my apps on a non-jailbroken device.  I hate that once you've written an iPhone app, they basically blackmail you into continuing to pay them because otherwise they take down your app, which means that it may not be accessible to paying customers if they need to wipe their phone and re-install their apps.  I hate their greedy policies with regards to content subscriptions.  I hate their underhanded payment system which is, as a matter of statistical certainty, allowing them to make interest on millions of dollars that are nominally owed to developers but will never actually be paid.  In general, I hate that they treat their developers like serfs just because they can, even though those same developers made their platform what it is today.<br /><br />

I hope that properly illustrates how much I hate Apple's policies, and I hope that it underscores the significance of what I'm about to say: from a pragmatic perspective, I'd <em>still</em> rather be developing for iOS because Google's development tools are <em>complete garbage.</em> I write all my code in vim, so I'm really not that picky, but I can only take so much of using Eclipse and having it literally <em>delete</em> my art assets from the file system.  (Not just removing them from the project - it literally deletes the files, seemingly at random.  I've never lost any work because of this, but it's extremely frustrating nevertheless.)  Not to mention the Android emulator: it's practically unusable for regular apps, and for games, forget about it.  You're lucky if you get 5 FPS.<br /><br />

Even if I buy an iPhone, I do still want to finish my game for Android.  The code is cross-platform, so if I could compile and test it using Xcode in the meantime... even just using the iPhone simulator, since it can actually run games at a reasonable framerate... it would save me a lot of headaches.  Either way I'll have to compile my app for Windows or iOS to do any marketing; taking screenshots of an Android app is difficult, and taking video is, as far as I can tell, impossible unless you have a phone with HDMI out and a capture card.  Ridiculous.</li>

    <li>The behavior of the back button is inconsistent, and developers use it as
    a crutch rather than thinking about and carefully designing a proper workflow
    through their applications.  I was arguing about this behavior with someone on
    Reddit a while ago, and I found a good comment on Hacker News about it:
    <br/><br />

<blockquote>I just got an Android with that great Virgin Mobile deal, and I was surprised
at just how much the Back button is used in almost all contexts. It's severely
overloaded: want to get out of an on-screen keyboard? Back. Want to move back
a screen? Back, except when it's Google Reader that opened a Browser window,
in which case it takes you back to the previous page that Browser had. Back
through a menu? Back. Back to a previous page in Browser? Back.

It's as if people just substituted the button for any instance in human language
where "back" was used."</blockquote>

...(and another)...<br /><br />

<blockquote>"Back" to some random place most of the time.<br />
1. receive email notification for two messages.<br />
2. click notification bar<br />
3. go to gmail app.<br />
4. open first message and click a link.<br />
5. you are now in the browser. (clicking back will close the window, but you want to read it later!)<br />
6. you long press HOME button (hoping to select gmail and read the other message)<br />
7. gmail is not in the open app list (WTH?!)\<br />
8. you curse, click home, find the gmail app, click it.<br />
9. now you are on the message with the link<br />
10. press BACK<br />
11. now you are on the message list (aha! not you home screen you came from!)<br />
12. click the 2nd message and read it
</blockquote>

In fairness, I'm of two minds about this because the back button does save a lot of screen real-estate by removing the necessity for on-screen navigation controls.  However, I'm not sure how much of an advantage that is in the face of the confusion it sometimes causes.</li>

<li>[This wasn't included in my e-mail to my friend, because I didn't know about it at the time.  I'm adding it now because it's fairly important.] Android can actually <em><a href="http://forum.xda-developers.com/showthread.php?p=12765846">lose SMS messages.</a></em>  That's completely unacceptable on a phone.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Android UI/UX gripes]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2011/04/16/android-uiux-gripes/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-16T22:08:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2011/04/16/android-uiux-gripes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The week before last, whilst browsing <a href="http://reddit.com">Reddit</a> I came across a blog by the name of <a href="http://android-gripes.tumblr.com/">&ldquo;Android Gripes.&rdquo;</a> The name is perhaps a bit misleading, as it&rsquo;s not actually a blog by an Android user hoping to spur Google into making UI improvements, as I would have expected.  It is, rather, a blog by a self-proclaimed Apple fanboy (though he&rsquo;s recently <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/Android/comments/glbjz/android_gripes_why_do_apps_from_the_same_company/c1ogv3q">edited his about page to remove that admission</a>) complaining about Android for the sake of&hellip; well, complaining about Android.<!-- more --></p>

<p>That might be a little unfair.  Perhaps I should let the author speak for himself:</p>

<blockquote>I have constantly heard many gripes about Android. Recently I happened to have access to some Android phones and use them in a daily base. The more I use Android, the more I feel that Android is indeed a half-baked OS, its UX/UI is horrible and various hardwares are poorly designed. It’s true that those phones are working like smartphones, better than feature phones from old school, but they ignore a lot of the details. Just for Google’s own benefit, they helped handset manufactures brutally dumped a huge amount of unpolished devices to the market. They made people think this is how smartphones should work. This is so unfair to consumers. <strong>IMHO, it is no different from committing a crime.</strong> That’s why I made the cartoon of "Android Gripes" as a Monopoly "Go Directly To Jail" card showing an Android on it.

As much as I believe in Apple, I think everybody deserves great user experience, especially when it comes to phones. I think it is my mission to let more people know that Android does not provide you that. Android only provides inferior user experience. You either admit it and bear with it, or go for better alternatives. That’s why I started writing this blog.</blockquote>


<p>(Emphasis added.)  English is not the author&rsquo;s native language, so you&rsquo;ll have to excuse the occasionally odd grammar.  It&rsquo;s immediately apparent that the author&rsquo;s stated opinion of Android is patently absurd; bad UI/UX can have many negative consequences, but it is certainly not criminal.  Redditors have also <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/Android/comments/glbjz/android_gripes_why_do_apps_from_the_same_company/">pointed out</a> that a number of comparisons the Android Gripes author makes are somewhat unfair.  For instance, he <a href="http://android-gripes.tumblr.com/post/4409289546/why-do-apps-from-the-same-company-look-worse-on-android">compares old, oudated Android apps</a> against apps which were recently updated on iOS, and misleadingly remarks on &ldquo;extra&rdquo; (meaning blank) space in the Facebook app.  The blank space in question <em>does</em> contain content when one is signed into a legitimate profile.</p>

<p>With all of that said, I&rsquo;m not writing this post to refute the Android Gripes author.  I actually agree with an unfortunate number of his points.  While there&rsquo;s a lot that can be said about where the iPhone&rsquo;s UI/UX fails (I&rsquo;ve <a href="http://www.mlindgren.ca/archives/151">previously mentioned</a> their complete lack of a workable notification system), excuses and rationalizations won&rsquo;t do anything to improve the state of Android apps.  Even if you believe that Android&rsquo;s UI/UX is better than Apple&rsquo;s (and I do feel that that&rsquo;s a hard case to make), I think it&rsquo;s undeniable that there&rsquo;s room for improvement.  It&rsquo;s certainly worth mentioning that some of the Android Gripe&rsquo;s authors examples are misleading, but what&rsquo;s more important is that we—that is to say, Android developers—ask ourselves where we&rsquo;re failing users, why it&rsquo;s happening, and what we can do to improve the platform.  In a future post, I&rsquo;ll offer my perspective on where Android could be improved.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
