<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Links | mlindgren.ca]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/categories/links/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-21T01:39:09-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.mlindgren.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mitch Lindgren]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
    <entry>
      




<title type="html"><![CDATA[Windows Hello, Microsoft Passport, and Tamriel Unlimited]]></title>
<link href="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2015/03/17/windows-hello/"/>
<updated>2015-03-17T23:28:10-07:00</updated>
<id>http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2015/03/17/windows-hello</id>

      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Lots of exciting news today! First off, Microsoft has made a couple exciting announcements about
Windows 10. Full disclosure: I am a Microsoft employee, so I am posting these for self-interested
reasons, but I&rsquo;m also genuinely really excited about what they mean for Windows.</p>

<p>The two new features are called <a href="http://blogs.windows.com/bloggingwindows/2015/03/17/making-windows-10-more-personal-and-more-secure-with-windows-hello/">Windows Hello and Microsoft Passport</a>.
Windows Hello is a software feature which, with supported hardware, offers &ldquo;biometric authentication
which can provide instant access to your Windows 10 devices.&rdquo; But Windows Hello is not just the same
old support for fingerprint readers that Windows has had for many years now; it &ldquo;enables you to
authenticate applications, enterprise content, and even certain online experiences without a
password being stored on your device or in a network server at all.&rdquo;</p>

<p>To accomplish that, Windows Hello works in conjunction with Microsoft Passport, which enables you to
&ldquo;securely authenticate to applications, websites and networks [&hellip;] without sending up a password.
Thus, there is no shared password stored on their servers for a hacker to potentially compromise.&rdquo;
You can read the linked article for the full details, but if you just want the overview, watch this
video:</p>

<div style="position: relative; height: 480px;">
<iframe width="854" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/1AsoSnOmhvU" frameborder="0"
allowfullscreen style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%"></iframe>
</div>


<p><br /></p>

<p>Second, as of today, <a href="http://www.elderscrollsonline.com/en-us/news/post/2015/03/17/welcome-to-tamriel-unlimited">The Elder Scrolls Online: Tamriel Unlimited</a>
has launched, meaning that ESO no longer requires a subscription to play. You&rsquo;ll still have to buy
the base game, but after that, no subscription is required to log in. I
<a href="/entry/2014/05/18/the-elder-scrolls-online/">previously wrote</a> a very favorable review of The
Elder Scrolls Online, and while I haven&rsquo;t had much time to play it over the past few months, I do
still log in occasionally, and I still enjoy the game. I&rsquo;m hoping this change to the payment model
will bring in new players, because at this point the game&rsquo;s biggest problem seems to be long dungeon
queue times; I can only assume this is due to a population that has dwindled since launch
almost a year ago.</p>

<p>Truth be told, I have mixed feelings about Tamriel Unlimited. I think there are significant merits
to the subscription-based model that many players don&rsquo;t recognize, and the progress that Zenimax
Online Studios has made since ESO&rsquo;s release is a testament to that: they&rsquo;ve released six significant
content patches with features including a new zone, multiple new dungeons and Trials (think raids),
new facial and combat animations, a new endgame character advancement system and drastic
rebalancing, a justice system, and dozens more improvements. I worry that the focus will now shift
from gameplay enhancements to purchasable cosmetic items, because the latter may be more of a cash
cow for the company. I also have more general concerns about the continuing trend of people
expecting everything on the Internet to be free&hellip; but that&rsquo;s a topic for another post.</p>

<p>That said, I&rsquo;m willing to give Tamriel Unlimited the benefit of the doubt. It could be that this
payment model change is just what the game needs to bring it the market success I&rsquo;ve always felt it
deserved. If you played ESO previously but have since quit, it&rsquo;s well worth picking up again; if
you&rsquo;ve never played before, I would sincerely urge you to give it a try. Either way, take a look at
the launch trailer below, which shows off some of the enhancements that have been made since the
game&rsquo;s release:</p>

<div style="position: relative; height: 480px;">
<iframe width="854" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/D0c08A3vswQ" frameborder="0"
allowfullscreen style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%"></iframe>
</div>


<p><br /></p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      




<title type="html"><![CDATA[The care and feeding of software engineers &#x22EF;]]></title>
<link href="http://www.nczonline.net/blog/2012/06/12/the-care-and-feeding-of-software-engineers-or-why-engineers-are-grumpy/"/>
<updated>2015-01-26T00:48:10-08:00</updated>
<id>http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2015/01/26/the-care-and-feeding-of-software-engineers</id>

      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Via a friend&rsquo;s Facebook feed comes this
<a href="http://www.nczonline.net/blog/2012/06/12/the-care-and-feeding-of-software-engineers-or-why-engineers-are-grumpy/">excellent article</a>
about &ldquo;the psychology of software engineers and what makes us the way we are.&rdquo;
I&rsquo;m in almost complete agreement with the article, although I do somewhat take
issue with this paragraph:</p>

<blockquote><p>Part of the problem [of software engineers consistently giving overoptimistic
estimates and then failing to meet them] is also our fragile egos. We get
afraid that if we give an estimate that is &ldquo;too long&rdquo;, that people will think
less of us.  &ldquo;Good engineers&rdquo; should be able to work faster, they say, and so
we acquiesce.</p></blockquote>

<p>I don&rsquo;t really think software engineers in general have &ldquo;fragile egos,&rdquo; or at
least not to a greater extent than people in any other profession. We <em>are</em>
notoriously bad at giving realistic estimates, but in my experience, this is
often because we&rsquo;re actually incentivized to do so: deadlines are set before the
amount of work required for a project is actually determined, or without regard
to it, and then we&rsquo;re made to fit our estimates into too-short iterations while
still trying to accomplish all we set out to do. There&rsquo;s a common sentiment that
it&rsquo;s better to be under-optimistic and out-perform your goals than the converse,
and while that seems true in theory, in practice there don&rsquo;t seem to be many
discouragements to failing to live up to estimates that everyone already knows
are unrealistic and often meaningless.</p>

<p>By contrast, I think the fear that people will think less of us for giving &ldquo;too
long&rdquo; estimates is completely valid in a culture where it&rsquo;s commonplace to set
unrealistic goals and then break our backs trying to achieve them by any means
necessary. I think this especially true at the feature team level when one is
working on a large piece of software. What do you expect to happen to a team
that estimates up front that its feature cannot be completed within the release
window? (Remember,
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Mythical_Man-Month">adding more engineers might just make the problem worse</a>.)
I think it&rsquo;s safe to say that it won&rsquo;t involve promotions and pay raises.</p>

<p>Finally, as my wife pointed out when we discussed this article, the
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planning_fallacy">planning fallacy</a> is by no means
unique to software engineers.</p>

<p>All of that said, I think the rest of the article is very good; this part in
particular struck a chord for me (emphasis mine):</p>

<blockquote><p>So, without enough information, changing requirements, not enough knowledge to
do the job, and people constantly second guessing us, we trudge into work
every day. Being creative people, we put up with all of this because we know
that one day people will use our work. <strong>That&rsquo;s really what drives software
engineers more than anything else: the idea that people we don&rsquo;t even know
will be affected by our work.</strong> Whether you’re working on a web site visited
by millions each day or you’re working on a point-of-sale system for
restaurants, the knowledge that we’re affecting people&rsquo;s lives is a powerful
driver.</p></blockquote>

<p><a rel="bookmark" href="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2015/01/26/the-care-and-feeding-of-software-engineers/">&infin; Permalink</a></p>

]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      




<title type="html"><![CDATA[Be a Communications Consequentialist &#x22EF;]]></title>
<link href="http://measureofdoubt.com/2012/06/11/be-a-communications-consequentialist/"/>
<updated>2015-01-04T20:41:51-08:00</updated>
<id>http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2015/01/04/be-a-communications-consequentialist</id>

      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Via <a href="http://slatestarcodex.com/2015/01/01/untitled/#comment-170665">a comment on Slate Star Codex</a>,
<a href="http://measureofdoubt.com/">Measure of Doubt</a> discusses some strategies for
effective written communication, using a &ldquo;consequentialist&rdquo; approach. This is
probably the one I need to work on most:</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>Shorten posts.</strong> Presenting readers with an epic saga and expecting them to read
it all carefully is asking a lot. Ben Radford has an interesting post
<a href="http://www.centerforinquiry.net/blogs/show/people_dont_read_and_why_it_matters/">bemoaning that people don&rsquo;t read</a>.
It&rsquo;s 1,380 words – appropriate for some audiences, not for others. If my posts
get over 1,000 words, I look for ways to trim them or break them into separate
posts.</p></blockquote>

<p>Good advice, although I think the point that long posts may be more or less
appropriate for different audiences is underemphasized. Personally, I quite
enjoy the occasional 10,000 word epic.</p>

<p><a rel="bookmark" href="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2015/01/04/be-a-communications-consequentialist/">&infin; Permalink</a></p>

]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      




<title type="html"><![CDATA[Review Link: In Real Life &#x22EF;]]></title>
<link href="http://shayshortt.com/2014/12/02/in-real-life/"/>
<updated>2014-12-24T02:00:00-08:00</updated>
<id>http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2014/12/24/review-link-in-real-life</id>

      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m in the process of writing another book review, but as usual, it&rsquo;s turning
out to be longer than I expected. In the meantime, I&rsquo;d like to direct all zero
of you who are just <em>dying</em> to know my opinions on literature to
<a href="http://shayshortt.com/2014/12/02/in-real-life/">this review</a> of Cory Doctorow
and Jen Wang&rsquo;s <em>In Real Life</em>, written by <a href="http://shayshortt.com">my wife</a>.
I&rsquo;m not going to make a habit of linking to every one of her reviews (especially
given that she writes them far more frequently than I update this site), but
having also read <em>In Real Life</em> (on her recommendation), I wholeheartedly agree
with her assessment and have little to add. Any comments should be directed to
her post.</p>

<p>My next review should be posted soon.</p>

<p><a rel="bookmark" href="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2014/12/24/review-link-in-real-life/">&infin; Permalink</a></p>

]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      




<title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Mozilla Persona Is the Right Answer to the Question of Identity &#x22EF;]]></title>
<link href="http://labs.newsint.co.uk/blog/2012/10/why-mozilla-persona-is-the-right-answer-to-the-question-of-identity/"/>
<updated>2012-10-03T20:37:00-07:00</updated>
<id>http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2012/10/03/why-mozilla-persona-is-the-right-answer-to-the-question-of-identity</id>

      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>[Updated December 24th, 2014: I&rsquo;m leaving this post here for historical
purposes, but I no longer endorse Mozilla Persona. There are a number of reasons
for this, but one of the primary ones is that the project does not seem to have
gained any momentum in the two years since I wrote this post. At this point I am
skeptical that it ever will gain that momentum.]</em></p>

<p>David Somers presents an
<a href="http://labs.newsint.co.uk/blog/2012/10/why-mozilla-persona-is-the-right-answer-to-the-question-of-identity/">excellent rundown</a>
of what
<a href="http://www.mozilla.org/en-US/persona/">Mozilla Persona</a> is and why it&rsquo;s
currently the best option for identity and authentication for web services. I&rsquo;ve
implemented authentication using Persona in the
<a href="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2012/09/14/social-networks-and-content-ownership/">photo album app</a>
I&rsquo;m working on, and I found it remarkably easy to integrate with my app. And, as
David explains, Persona is also much easier for users to understand than
competing platforms like OpenID. If you&rsquo;re a web developer, you really need to
add Persona support to your application as soon as
possible. It can be done in literally a matter of minutes, and if Persona takes
off the benefit to identity management on the Internet could be huge.</p>

<p>Perhaps my favourite thing about Persona is that it gives me the opportunity to
<a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Persona/Implementing_a_Persona_IdP">implement my own identity provider</a>,
which means I can have <em>complete</em> control over how I authenticate to any
Persona-consuming service. I could have <em>n</em>-factor authentication, with no limit
on the complexity or specificity of the factors besides my own imagination. For
example, I could generate SSL client certificates for each of my machines and
hardcode their thumbprints into my identity provider to ensure that it wouldn&rsquo;t
even service requests from machines I haven&rsquo;t explicitly added.  Or if I wanted
to get creative, I could have my identity provider generate a random temporary
key which I would have to retrieve via SSH (but this is less convenient and
probably also less secure than doing SSL client authentication.) The
possibilities are endless.</p>

<p>Perhaps an end is finally in sight to the frustration of having dozens upon
dozens of different accounts and passwords for various services,
<a href="http://me.veekun.com/blog/2011/12/04/fuck-passwords/">each with its own uniquely nonsensical password composition policy</a>.  Everyone needs to implement Persona&mdash;preferably yesterday.</p>

<p><a rel="bookmark" href="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2012/10/03/why-mozilla-persona-is-the-right-answer-to-the-question-of-identity/">&infin; Permalink</a></p>

]]></content>
    </entry>
  
</feed>

