<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Reviews | mlindgren.ca]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/categories/reviews/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-10T02:12:56-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.mlindgren.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mitch Lindgren]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
    <entry>
      




<title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Highlights: Halo: The Fall of Reach]]></title>
<link href="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2015/01/02/book-highlights-halo-the-fall-of-reach/"/>
<updated>2015-01-02T20:03:24-08:00</updated>
<id>http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2015/01/02/book-highlights-halo-the-fall-of-reach</id>

      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As the first book set in the Halo universe, Eric Nylund&rsquo;s <em>Halo: The Fall of
Reach</em> describes the training and induction of the first-ever Spartans,
including <a href="http://halo.wikia.com/wiki/John-117">John-117</a>, the Master Chief. It
follows the Spartans through some of their earliest missions, depicts humanity&rsquo;s
first contact with the <a href="http://halo.wikia.com/wiki/Covenant_Empire">Covenant</a>,
and culminates in the battle for planet Reach, a human colony. I don&rsquo;t often
read fiction, and I am not sure I&rsquo;ve ever before read &ldquo;expanded universe&rdquo;
fiction for a game or a movie, so <em>Halo: The Fall of Reach</em> was a bit of an
unusual read for me. However, since I really enjoy the <em>Halo</em> games, universe,
and characters, and since this book came highly recommended by other fans of the
series, I figured it couldn&rsquo;t hurt to give it a try.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, per my <a href="/about/#review_policy">review policy</a>, I can&rsquo;t actually
review this book: the <em>Halo</em> series, and indeed the copyright to the book, is
owned by Microsoft, by whom I am employed by. Instead, I want to highlight a
few things that I found interesting in the book. <strong>Be warned that this post will
contain some spoilers for the book and other parts of the <em>Halo</em> series.</strong></p>

<!-- more -->


<ul>
<li><p>I&rsquo;ve never been involved in professional game development, but my
understanding is that game mechanics and environments are typically built
first, with story added later in the development process; this necessarily
means that the plot is shoehorned into a set of scenarios and environments
that might not actually be an optimal fit for it. This in turn is one of the
reasons video game writing is notoriously mediocre. To the extent that this is
true, it is especially true of the first game in a new franchise. However,
<em>Halo: The Fall of Reach</em> was actually originally published on October 30th,
2001, about two weeks <em>before</em> <em>Halo: Combat Evolved</em> was released. This shows
that Bungie had an impressively thorough understanding of the universe they
were building at that relatively early stage in the franchise&rsquo;s life.</p></li>
<li><p>On the other hand, much of that universe might still have been conceived in a
short amount of time. In an afterword to the <em>Halo: The Fall of Reach</em>,
<a href="http://halo.wikia.com/wiki/Frank_O%27Connor">Frank O&#8217;Connor</a> writes
that &ldquo;[t]he book went from conception to final print in a staggering four
months.&rdquo; That is certainly impressive for 352-page book!</p></li>
<li><p>According to the book, Spartans in MJOLNIR armor are able to sprint at
superhuman speeds: &ldquo;The Chief and his team sprinted up the half-kilometer
sandstone slope in thirty-two seconds flat.&rdquo; That is a speed of 35 miles per
hour (56.2km/h) on an upward slope. This is somewhat at odds with the
relatively sluggish pace of movement in the first three Halo games. However,
sprinting was fairly unpopular when it was added to the game series, as
many people felt that it changed multiplayer balance for the worse. (I don&rsquo;t
personally have an opinion on that, but obviously, gameplay balance is more
important than being accurate to lore.)</p></li>
<li><p>On the subject of gameplay being at odds with lore, the game <em>Halo: Reach</em>
also depicts the fall of Reach, but from the perspective of a group of Spartans
on the ground rather than from the Master Chief&rsquo;s perspective. It also
infamously retcons some significant portions of the plot laid out in <em>The Fall
of Reach</em>. I haven&rsquo;t actually played <em>Halo: Reach</em> in several years, but going
back and reading the plot summary
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halo:_Reach">on Wikipedia</a>, I can immediately see
a number of differences from the events depicted in the book.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Final warning: spoilers begin here!</strong> At the beginning of <em>Halo: Combat
Evolved</em>, the UNSC ship <em>Pillar of Autumn</em> is supposed to have made a random
<a href="http://halo.wikia.com/wiki/Slipstream_Space">slipspace</a> jump to retreat from
a Covenant fleet&mdash;it&rsquo;s not mentioned in the game that the ship is
retreating from the lost battle for Reach. This is how the humanity first
happens upon the Halo rings (and, in fact, how the Covenant find them as well).
I always had trouble suspending disbelief that a jump to some <em>random</em> point in
the universe would result in the discovery of one of the handful of Halo rings
that exist.  But it turns out that the jump wasn&rsquo;t actually random: Cortana
chose the jump coordinates based on ancient navigation symbols found on an
artifact that the Master Chief had recovered from the Covenant after they
invaded the human colony world of Sigma Octanus IV.</p></li>
<li><p>Similarly, I had trouble suspending disbelief about the concept of
<a href="http://halo.wikia.com/wiki/Rampancy">AI rampancy</a>, at least as described in
the game, when it was introduced in <em>Halo 4</em>. Frankly, I thought the whole
thing was a fairly stupid plot device. But, actually, rampancy <em>wasn&rsquo;t</em>
introduced in <em>Halo 4</em>; it was a known phenomenon in the Halo universe right
from the start, and is mentioned at the same time as Cortana is introduced.
I&rsquo;m still not sure I&rsquo;m totally on board with the concept, but it does feel
less idiosyncratic now that I know that it was established long before being
reintroduced in <em>Halo 4</em>. Originally, I viewed it as something 343 added to
introduce tension to the romantic subplot between Cortana and the Master Chief,
but it turns out they were actually strictly following existing lore the whole
time:</p>

<blockquote><p>Cortana was a &ldquo;smart&rdquo; AI, an advanced artificial construct. Actually, the
terms <em>smart</em> and <em>dumb</em> as applied to AIs, were misleading; all AIs were
extraordinarily intelligent. But Cortana was special.</p>

<p>So-called dumb AIs within the set limits of their dynamic memory-processing
matrix were brilliant in their fields but were lacking in &ldquo;creativity.&rdquo; Déjà,
for example, was a &ldquo;dumb&rdquo; AI&mdash;incredibly useful, but limited.</p>

<p>Smart AIs like Cortana, however, had no limits on their dynamic
memory-processor matrix. Knowledge and creativity could grow unchecked.</p>

<p>She would pay a price for her genius, however. Such growth eventually led to
self-interference. Cortana would one day literally start thinking too much at
the expense of her normal functions. It was as if a human were to think with
so much of his brain that he stopped sending impulses to his heart and lungs.</p>

<p>Like all other smart AIs that Dr. Halsey had worked with over the years,
Cortana would effectively &ldquo;die&rdquo; after an operational life of seven years.</p></blockquote></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      




<title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review: I Am Malala]]></title>
<link href="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2014/12/26/book-review-i-am-malala/"/>
<updated>2014-12-26T01:57:00-08:00</updated>
<id>http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2014/12/26/book-review-i-am-malala</id>

      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I expect most people will already have some familiarity with Malala Yousafzai.
In case you&rsquo;ve been living under a rock, though, Malala is a young Pakistani
woman who, at the age of 15, was shot in the head by the Taliban for her
outspoken support of the right to education of children, including (especially)
girls, who are often denied the right due to their gender. Miraculously, she
survived the assassination attempt, and following her recovery, has continued to
campaign in support of education. Now, at age 17, she has an impressive list of
accomplishments and accolades to her name, including most recently becoming the
youngest Nobel laureate in history after jointly winning the 2014 Peace Prize
with Kailash Satyarthi, another activist for children&rsquo;s rights.</p>

<p><em>I Am Malala: The Girl Who Stood Up for Education and Was Shot by the Taliban</em>,
written jointly with award-winning foreign correspondent Christina Lamb, is
Malala&rsquo;s autobiography. It chronicles her experience growing up in Pakistan&rsquo;s
Swat Valley, the invasion of the Taliban into the area and her life under their
rule, their attempt on her life, and her recovery and continuing efforts in
support of education.<!-- more --></p>

<div style="float: right; max-width: 30%; margin: 5px;">
<a href="http://www.malala.org/">
<img src="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/images/IAmMalala.jpg"
style="max-height: 300px"
alt="I Am Malala: The Girl Who Stood Up for Education and Was Shot by the
Taliban, by Malala Yousafzai and Christina Lamb. Image copyright Hachette Book
Group Inc, used under fair use" />
</a>
</div>


<p>Before I continue, I have a caveat about this review. Reviews always contain
elements of subjectivity, and there&rsquo;s nothing wrong with that per se: art, after
all, is in the eye of the beholder. But a reviewer must endeavor to keep his own
biases in check, and in particular, to separate his opinion of the creator from
his judgment of the creation. In that respect, this review is difficult to
write. I believe that Malala Yousafzai is the most courageous and heroic person
alive today, and that her campaign has the potential to be among the most
important activist movements of the 21st century. The emancipation and education
of oppressed, powerless and impoverished women and girls in developing countries
is vitally important to global stability and progress, and Malala has become not
only an internationally-recognized figurehead for this struggle, but also,
through <a href="http://www.malala.org/">her foundation</a> and her speeches, one of the
most important leaders in effecting a solution.</p>

<p>Naturally, then, I find I have a hard time criticizing Malala&rsquo;s work, and you
should bear that in mind as you read this review. Despite any effort to the
contrary, I will likely be more forgiving to this book than I would be to a book
written by someone for whom I did not have such great respect.</p>

<p>It is unfortunate, then, that I must admit that this book took me almost a year
to read, and not due to its length: even including a short glossary and
timeline, it&rsquo;s barely more than 300 pages. The problem was that I just didn&rsquo;t
find the first third of the book very interesting, so I started reading it very
slowly, and then eventually put it down for a long time, only returning to it
recently.</p>

<p>The first chapters of <em>I Am Malala</em> mainly serve as context for the rest of the
book. Malala first describes the history of Pakistan and of her family,
including much of her father&rsquo;s life before she was born. Her father, Ziauddin
Yousafzai, is shown to be an ambitious and courageous person in his own right:
his own dream was to be an educator, and as a young college graduate, he quickly
progressed from teaching English in a private college to setting up his own
school.  He then tenaciously oversaw his school&rsquo;s development into a sizable and
successful institution, despite many setbacks including considerable financial
hardship and a natural disaster which all but destroyed the school building.</p>

<p>Malala also describes her father&rsquo;s respect for women, which no doubt played a
formative role in her iron-willed personality, and which she contrasts with the
rest of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pashtun_people">Pashtun</a> culture:</p>

<blockquote><p>For most Pashtuns it&rsquo;s a gloomy day when a daughter is born. My father&rsquo;s
cousin Jehan Sher Khan Yousafzai was one of the few who came to celebrate my
birth and even gave a handsome gift of money. Yet, he brought with him a vast
family tree of our clan, the Dalokhel Yousafzai, going right back to my
great-great-grandfather and showing only the male line. My father, Ziauddin,
is different from most Pashtun men. He took the tree, drew a line like a
lollipop from his name and at the end of it he wrote, &ldquo;Malala.&rdquo; His cousin
laughed in astonishment. My father didn&rsquo;t care.</p></blockquote>

<p>Much of the rest of the opening of the book describes Malala&rsquo;s life in Mingora,
from broad details about the general character of life in Swat (which will
probably seem to most Western readers to be a peculiar mix of semi-modern
technology, patchwork infrastructure, and ancient cultural traditions), to
specifics such as her reputation in school as a talented and dedicated student.
All of this is necessary background, particularly for Westerners such as myself
who haven&rsquo;t the slightest clue what life in Pakistan is like, so I don&rsquo;t fault
Yousafzai and Lamb for including it in the book&mdash;but, well, it&rsquo;s just not
very interesting to read. Perhaps it&rsquo;s the linear, matter-of-fact way in which
it&rsquo;s written, or perhaps it&rsquo;s the marked similarity of Malala&rsquo;s life before the
Taliban occupation to that of a typical schoolchild, but I found myself
struggling to get through this section.</p>

<p>And yet, peculiarly, this section also seems to be short on some basic factual
details; for instance, until I looked it up for this review, I had pictured
Mingora as a small, rural city. In fact, though, its population was 175,000 in
1998&mdash;sixteen years ago, so it&rsquo;s likely grown considerably since then. The
city <em>I</em> grew up in has less than half that population today. Thus, my
perception as I read the book was greatly skewed in this respect, but it needn&rsquo;t
have been given all of the other details provided about Swat and Mingora.</p>

<p>The pace of the book picks up as the Talibanization of the Swat Valley begins in
2007, when Malala is ten years old.
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fazlullah_(militant_leader)">Maulana Fuzlullah</a>,
now a highly ranked militant leader in the Pakistani Taliban, started a radio
broadcast in which he professed his interpretation of Islam. Fazlullah&rsquo;s
broadcasts started innocently enough:</p>

<blockquote><p>He used his station to encourage people to adopt good habits and abandon
practices he said were bad. He said men should keep their beards but give up
smoking and using the tobacco they liked to chew. He said people should
stop using heroin, and <em>chars</em>, which is our word for hashish.</p></blockquote>

<p>Over time, though, Fazlullah became increasingly radical and fundamentalist:
claiming that sinful actions such as &ldquo;listening to music, watching movies and
dancing&rdquo; had caused a recent earthquake; instructing women to never leave their
homes except in emergencies, and to always be veiled while in public; and
referring to the Pakistani government as infidels, stating that &ldquo;his men would
&lsquo;enforce [Sharia law] and tear [government officials] to pieces.&rsquo;&rdquo; By 2007
Fazlullah had become a powerful and influential figure within the Pakistani
Taliban, and on the 12th of July, following the
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Lal_Masjid">Red Mosque siege</a>, he
declared war on the Pakistani government.</p>

<p>The Taliban continued to spread throughout the Swat valley. By 2009, the
Talibanization had become so widespread that even local politicians, including
the area&rsquo;s deputy commissioner, were involved: &ldquo;When the highest authority in
your district joins the Taliban, then Talibanization becomes normal.&rdquo; As they
gained more and more political power, they also began enforcing their strict
interpretation of Islamic doctrine through threats and outright violence. They
issued an edict banning the education of girls, and meted out brutal punishments
for &ldquo;immoral&rdquo; acts such as dancing or wearing clothes &ldquo;incorrectly.&rdquo; There were
bombings, executions, and public whippings.</p>

<p>It was during this time that Malala began writing, at the behest of the BBC,
&ldquo;a diary about life under the Taliban.&rdquo; This diary was
<a href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/7834402.stm">published online</a> as part of
the BBC&rsquo;s coverage of the situation in Swat, but Malala used the pseudonym &ldquo;Gul
Makai&rdquo; due to the great danger inherent in criticizing the Taliban. The diary
only lasted until a few months, though. The Pakistani army had been trying for
some time, noncommittally and mostly ineffectively, to push back the Taliban,
but after a brief ceasefire, in May of 2009 they launched a full-scale
operation, &ldquo;Operation True Path, to drive the Taliban out of Swat.&rdquo; This
resulted in an exodus of civilians from the valley, and thus Malala and her
family became &ldquo;Internally Displaced Persons,&rdquo; forced to leave their home for
nearly three months while the army effected its campaign to take back Swat.</p>

<p>The campaign ended with the army claiming victory in July of 2009, and Malala
and her family were able to return home. But, predictably, the army&rsquo;s successful
campaign could not completely or permanently rid the valley of Taliban:</p>

<blockquote><p>In Swat we began to see more signs that the Taliban had never really left. Two
more schools were blown up and three foreign aid workers from a Christian
group were kidnapped as they returned to their base in Mingora and then
murdered. We received other shocking news. My father&rsquo;s friend Dr. Mohammad
Farooq, the vice chancellor of Swat University, had been killed by two gunmen
who burst into his office. Dr. Farooq was an Islamic scholar and former member
of the Jamaat-e-Islami party, and as one of the biggest voices against
Talibanization he had even issued a fatwa against suicide attacks.</p>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<p>Once again people started worrying that the Taliban were creeping back. But
whereas in 2008-9 there were many threats to all sorts of people, this time
the threats were specific to those who spoke against militants or the
high-handed behavior of the army.</p>

<p>&ldquo;The Taliban is not an organized force like we imagine,&rdquo; said my father&rsquo;s
friend Hidayatullah when they discussed it. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s a mentality, and this
mentality is everywhere in Pakistan. Someone who is against America, against
the Pakistan establishment, against English law, he has been infected by the
Taliban.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>Despite this, Malala continued speaking at events in support of education and
peace, and continued to gain national and international attention, including
winning Pakistan&rsquo;s National Peace Prize&mdash;a brand new award for which Malala
was the first recipient ever. But as we now know, this stubborn refusal to be
silenced would come at great cost to her.</p>

<p>On Tuesday, October 9th, 2012, Malala was shot in the head by a young Taliban
gunman as she rode the school bus home. This chapter, in contrast to the
terrible event it recounts, is probably the best written in the book. Malala
describes every minute detail of the moments leading up to the assassination
attempt: the sounds from the shops along the road, the smell of the air, and
then the sudden, ominous absence of people in the street. The style here
precisely communicates the feeling of a memory of a terrible event: the way
time seems to slow leading up to it, and how vividly we recall the mundane
circumstances and sensations it becomes associated with. Even though this is
the part of Malala&rsquo;s story that everyone already knows, it&rsquo;s pulse-quickening to
read in her own words, and at this point the book becomes very hard to put down.</p>

<p>The rest of the book, which comprises about a fifth of its total length,
describes Malala&rsquo;s treatment and recovery, and briefly illustrates her new life
in Birmingham, England. Living in England has given Malala the opportunity to
return to school, and to continue to speak in support of education for children,
without being in constant danger. Nevertheless, she misses her home in Swat, and
already has aspirations to return to Pakistan:</p>

<blockquote><p>I know I will go back to Pakistan, but whenever I tell my father I want to go
home, he finds excuses. &ldquo;No, [dear one], your treatment is not complete,&rdquo; he says,
or, &ldquo;These schools are good. You should stay here and gather knowledge so you
can use your words powerfully.&rdquo;</p>

<p>He is right. I want to learn and be trained well with the weapon of knowledge.
Then I will be able to fight more effectively for my cause.</p></blockquote>

<p>Here again, though, I wish <em>I Am Malala</em> provided more detail. Malala&rsquo;s cause is
clear, as is her fearless determination in pursuit of it. Still only seventeen
years old, she already has the recognition and support of the international
community, and a non-profit foundation in her name working towards her dream of
safe, free education for all children. But achieving this will be no easy task,
and I wish the book provided a more complete picture of Malala&rsquo;s vision. Besides
the overt threat of terrorist groups such as the Taliban, Malala and her
foundation will have to contend with poverty, war, cultural impediments to
learning, suspicion of the West and its influence, and innumerble other
challenges.  She has a long fight ahead of her. What is her plan?</p>

<p>Perhaps this is a lot to expect from a seventeen-year-old. But then, Malala has
very clearly demonstrated that she is no ordinary seventeen-year-old. I&rsquo;m sure
she has given some thought to these issues, and I wish her book had provided
more insight in that respect. For instance, she briefly mentions
<a href="http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2013/07/17/the-taliban-s-letter-to-malalayousafzai.html">a now-infamous letter</a>
she received from Taliban commander Adnan Rashid, who claims she was shot for
espousing what the Taliban view as a pro-Western, anti-Islamic ideology. She
barely dedicates a paragraph in response to this, but even here in the West
there are people who take Rashid&rsquo;s words at face value, as if his stance is
perfectly legitimate and reasonable. This is a problem that Malala will likely
have to contend with for as long as she continues to fight for her cause. What
will she do to solve it? I can only hope that details such as these will be the
subject of another book.</p>

<p>Much as I&rsquo;d like to, I can&rsquo;t say that <em>I Am Malala</em> is among the best books I&rsquo;ve
ever read. It is linear and factual to a fault, some of it written almost like a
narrated <acronym title="curriculum vitae">CV</acronym>, and is at times
ponderously paced. It seems to me to be more about what Malala has <em>done</em> than
who she <em>is</em>; for an autobiography, it feels curiously impersonal. That said,
the latter two-thirds of the book are still an enjoyable read, at least for
those who want to know more of Malala&rsquo;s story. Most importantly, whatever
quibbles I have with the way <em>I Am Malala</em> is written, it may well be one of the
most <em>important</em> books I&rsquo;ve ever read, because like Malala herself, it is a
testament to what can be accomplished through hope, dedication, and
perseverance.</p>

<p>I hope, and expect, that we will only hear more and more about Malala Yousafzai
as the years go on.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      




<title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review: Lying]]></title>
<link href="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2014/11/02/book-review-lying/"/>
<updated>2014-11-02T18:09:00-08:00</updated>
<id>http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2014/11/02/book-review-lying</id>

      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Originally published as a
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kindle_single">&ldquo;Kindle single&rdquo;</a> in 2011, Sam
Harris&#8217; <em><a href="http://www.samharris.org/lying">Lying</a></em> was republished in a revised
and expanded format in 2013, but it remains more of an essay than a book. The
entirety of the book weighs in at 108 pages, but the main content takes up only
about a third of that. The remaining two thirds consist of a transcript of a
conversation between Harris and professor Ronald A. Howard, whom Harris credits
as the inspiration for the book, and an FAQ based on feedback received since the
original publication. These latter two parts make a worthwhile addendum to the
original essay, but they are by no means indispensable: the centerpiece here is
Harris&#8217; analysis of the act of lying and all the ways in which it can lead to
bad outcomes.</p>

<p>In <em>Lying</em>, Harris attempts to make the case that dishonesty is almost always
unethical, and that simply by being truthful, one can avoid &ldquo;endless forms of
suffering and embarrassment.&rdquo; This might seem like a fairly obvious statement,
but Harris explicitly includes (and, in fact, primarily focuses on) &ldquo;white
lies&rdquo;&mdash;those small lies we tell not for our own benefit, but, we think, to
spare others from hurt feelings or unpalatable truths. Though white lies are
often told by good people for what they believe to be are good reasons, Harris
argues that the cost of these lies, in the long term, outweighs their benefit:</p>

<!-- more -->




<div style="float: right; max-width: 30%;">
<a href="http://www.samharris.org/free-will">
<img src="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/images/SamHarrisLying.jpg"
style="max-height: 300px"
alt="Lying by Sam Harris. Image copyright Sam Harris, used under fair use" />
</a>
</div>


<blockquote><p>What could be wrong with truly &ldquo;white&rdquo; lies? First, they are still lies. And
in telling them, we incur all the problems of being less than straightforward
in our dealings with other people. Sincerity, authenticity, integrity, mutual
understanding&mdash;these and other sources of moral wealth are destroyed the
moment we deliberately misrepresent our beliefs, whether or not our lies are
ever discovered.</p>

<p>And although we imagine that we tell certain lies out of compassion for
others, it is rarely difficult to spot the damage we do in the process. By
lying, we deny our friends access to reality&mdash;and their resulting
ignorance often harms them in ways we did not anticipate. Our friends may act
on our falsehoods, or fail to solve problems that could have been solved only
on the basis of good information. Rather often, to lie is to infringe on the
freedom of those we care about.</p>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<p>When we presume to lie for the benefit of others, we have decided that <em>we</em>
are the best judges of how much they should understand about their own
lives&mdash;about how they appear, their reputation, or their prospects in the
world. This is an extraordinary stance to adopt toward other human beings, and
it requires justification. Unless someone is suicidal or otherwise on the
brink, deciding how much he should know about himself seems the quintessence
of arrogance. What attitude could be more disrespectful of those we care
about?</p></blockquote>

<p>Harris provides a number of examples of how white lies can backfire: by
dishonestly telling a friend that he doesn&rsquo;t need to lose weight, you might be
denying him the motivation he needs to live a healthier lifestyle. By hiding a
serious medical diagnosis from loved ones, you foreshorten their opportunity to
come to terms with it, and miss a chance to deepen your relationship. By
providing false encouragement about a friend&rsquo;s career prospects, you lead her to
waste time and energy that might be spent more productively with a change of
course.</p>

<p>Although he does make a case for honesty in situations in which many of us would
be tempted to lie, Harris does not seem to be advocating for
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radical_Honesty">&ldquo;Radical Honesty&rdquo;</a>. Radical
Honesty, <a href="http://www.esquire.com/features/honesty0707">as I understand it</a>,
requires not only complete honesty, but also complete <em>transparency</em>, and what
some might call a stunning lack of tact. Harris, by contrast, allows that it may
sometimes be necessary to &ldquo;[hold] one&rsquo;s tongue, or [steer] a conversation toward
topics of relative safety&rdquo; in order to maintain civility. He also sees no
conflict in principle between being honest and keeping secrets: &ldquo;If someone asks
how much money you have in your bank account, you are under no ethical
obligation to tell him. The truth could well be &lsquo;I&rsquo;d rather not say.&rsquo;&rdquo;</p>

<p>Harris&#8217; position is certainly easier to embrace than &ldquo;Radical Honesty,&rdquo; which I
imagine could easily ruin your life if you don&rsquo;t have <em>extremely</em> understanding
friends and family. That said, it&rsquo;s still not easy, in practice, to always be
honest. It is hard to tell people things that you know they won&rsquo;t want to hear.
It takes willpower and emotional energy to always make the virtuous choice
rather than looking for the easy way out. And there are edge cases, rare but by
no means impossible, where the ethical value of honesty really does seem
questionable. For instance, consider this example from Harris&#8217; conversation with
professor Howard:</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>Harris:</strong> &hellip; Other examples of this [ethical difficulty] have come to me from
people who are caring for parents with dementia. Your mother wakes up every
morning wondering where your father is, but your father has been dead for
fifteen years. Every time you explain this, your mother has to relive the
bereavement process all over again, only to wake up the next morning looking
for her husband. Let&rsquo;s assume that when you lie, saying something like &ldquo;Oh,
he&rsquo;s away on a business trip,&rdquo; your mother very quickly forgets about your
father&rsquo;s absence and her grief doesn&rsquo;t get reactivated.</p>

<p><strong>Howard:</strong> That&rsquo;s an interesting one. I would be tempted to say something like
&ldquo;Well, he&rsquo;s where he usually is at this time of day.&rdquo; The fact that he&rsquo;s
buried in the ground somewhere doesn&rsquo;t add anything to this person&rsquo;s knowledge
of what&rsquo;s going on. And as you pointed out, you would just be putting her
through pain all over again. As you stated the case, why would you want to do
that?</p></blockquote>

<p>This answer doesn&rsquo;t seem entirely satisfactory. First of all, what if you were
asked for a more specific answer than the one Howard gave? In that case, I think
you really would be forced to lie, and from a consequentialist point of view
that really does seem like the right thing to do given the situation; Howard
almost admits as much. And even if that&rsquo;s not the case, Howard&rsquo;s answer still
seems deliberately designed to be deceptive, even if it is not strictly false.
He goes on to call this &ldquo;&lsquo;skillful truth-telling&rsquo; as opposed to &lsquo;evasion,&rsquo;&rdquo; but
that seems like a euphemism to me.</p>

<p>This exemplifies the problem I have with <em>Lying</em>. I&rsquo;m in complete agreement with
Harris that lying is almost never the right choice, for both ethical and
practical reasons. But believing that in principle is much different from
adhering to it in practice. How does we resist the almost reflexive impulse to
tell people only what we think they want to hear? Where do we draw the line
between reasonably concealing of private information and dishonestly withholding
facts that people have a right to know? And how can we train ourselves to
reliably decide when situations really do warrant &ldquo;skillful truth-telling&rdquo; if
not outright deception? These questions are not always easy to answer, and I
don&rsquo;t think that <em>Lying</em> does enough to address them.</p>

<p>If you find yourself to really be in need of convincing that white lies can be
harmful and should generally not be ethically permissible, then <em>Lying</em> is
probably a worthwhile read. But if you already accept that proposition, this
book is hard to recommend.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      




<title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review: Free Will]]></title>
<link href="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2014/10/26/book-review-free-will/"/>
<updated>2014-10-26T17:00:00-07:00</updated>
<id>http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2014/10/26/book-review-free-will</id>

      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sam Harris is a controversial figure, to say the least. Personally, I&rsquo;m a fan of
his work, but as one of the &ldquo;four horsemen&rdquo; of so-called New Atheism, he has
met with much ire since the publication of his first book. This comes not only
from religious adherents, but also from secular liberals, many of whom seem to
willfully (and sometimes maybe even <em>gleefully</em>) misinterpret him.  Although
<em><a href="http://www.samharris.org/free-will">Free Will</a>,</em> published in 2012, courts
less political controversy than Harris&#8217; other works, it too will raise the
eyebrows of some readers. In fact, earlier this year, it met with a prickly
reception from fellow &ldquo;horseman&rdquo; and philosophy professor Dan Dennett.</p>

<!-- more -->




<div style="float: right; max-width: 30%;">
<a href="http://www.samharris.org/free-will">
<img src="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/images/SamHarrisFreeWill.jpg"
style="max-height: 300px"
alt="Free Will by Sam Harris. Image copyright Sam Harris, used under fair use" />
</a>
</div>


<p>In <em>Free Will</em>, Harris lays out a case against the philosophical concept of the
same name. There are many facets to his argument, but I think his primary claims
can be enumerated as follows:</p>

<ol>
<li>Scientific research shows that &ldquo;determinism, in every sense relevant to human
behavior, is true. Unconscious neural events determine our thoughts and
actions&mdash;and are themselves determined by prior causes of which we are
subjectively unaware.&rdquo;</li>
<li><a href="http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/determinism-causal/">Determinism</a>
cannot be reconciled with (what Harris believes is) the popular conception of
free will. (In philosophical terms, this means that Harris takes an
<em>incompatibilist</em> stance on the relationship between determinism and free will.
He spends much of the book arguing against
<em><a href="http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/compatibilism/">compatibilism</a></em>, which is
a philosophy that tries to reconcile the concepts.)</li>
<li>Even if determinism were not true (due to, for example, randomness in quantum
events), free will would <em>still</em> not be possible, as in that case &ldquo;[our wills
would be] the product of chance and we [would not be] responsible for them.&rdquo;</li>
<li>Upon introspection, &ldquo;free will doesn&rsquo;t even correspond to any <em>subjective</em>
fact about us &hellip; Seeming acts of volition merely arise spontaneously (whether
caused, uncaused, or probabilistically inclined, it makes no difference) and
cannot be traced to a point of origin in our conscious minds.&rdquo;</li>
</ol>


<p>Harris begins with the scientific evidence for the determined nature of human
behavior. He writes:</p>

<blockquote><p>The physiologist Benjamin Libet famously used EEG to show that activity in the
brain&rsquo;s motor cortex can be detected some 300 milliseconds before a person
feels that he has decided to move. Another lab extended this work using
functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI): Subjects were asked to press one
of two buttons while watching a &ldquo;clock&rdquo; composed of a random sequence of
letters appearing on a screen. They reported which letter was visible at the
moment they decided to press one button or the other. The experimenters found
two brain regions that contained information about which buttons subjects
would press a full <em>7 to 10 seconds</em> before the decision was consciously made.
More recently, direct recordings from the cortex showed that the activity of
merely 256 neurons was sufficient to predict with 80 percent accuracy a
person&rsquo;s decision to move 700 milliseconds before he became aware of it.</p></blockquote>

<p>(Harris provides sources for each of these claims in the book, but I am not
reproducing the citations here for the sake of brevity.) These findings are
pretty remarkable in their own right, and will probably be quite unsettling to
some readers. This is also likely the only part of the book that will seem truly
novel to those already highly schooled in philosophy; the debate about free will
has been ongoing for centuries, and it seems unlikely to me that Harris&#8217; short
book (at less than 100 pages long) contains any truly novel philosophical
arguments. Even so, I&rsquo;m not sure the discussion of these studies will actually
work to Harris&#8217; advantage.  The core of his argument <em>is</em> philosophical, but
some readers are certain to get caught up in overthinking the scientific claims,
even though, as Harris himself states, nothing actually depends on them.</p>

<p>In fact, Harris goes so far as to say that even if one believes that
consciousness originates in a &ldquo;soul&rdquo; which is separate from and unconstrained by
our physical brains, that <em>still</em> would not make free will feasible: a soul
would not change the fact that we do not have full awareness of, let alone
control over, the origins of our thoughts and intentions. To use one of Harris&#8217;
examples:</p>

<blockquote><p>Why did I order beer instead of wine? Because I prefer beer. Why do I prefer
it? I don&rsquo;t know, but I generally have no need to ask. Knowing that I like
beer more than wine is all I need to know to function in a restaurant.
Whatever the reason, I prefer one taste to the other. Is there freedom in
this? None whatsoever. Would I magically reclaim my freedom if I decided to
spite my preference and order wine instead? No, because the roots of this
intention would be as obscure as the preference itself.</p></blockquote>

<p>Even with that example, I suspect this claim is likely to confuse many readers,
as a naïve reading of it will make it seem flatly absurd: you probably <em>can</em>
explain most of your thoughts and intentions with reference to your values,
preferences, duties, etc.  But Harris&#8217; point is that if you follow this chain of
causation back as far as possible, you will inevitably arrive at something you
either can&rsquo;t explain or have no control over. You might say that you prefer beer
over wine (or vice versa) because beer is more pleasing to your taste buds. But
<em>why</em> is it more pleasing? Probably, ultimately, because of your genes.
Obviously, you have no hand in that. (I hope I&rsquo;m not muddying the water by
adding that whatever you <em>think</em> your reasons for a given decision are,
<a href="http://www.texasenterprise.utexas.edu/article/do-you-make-buying-decisions-based-logic-or-emotion-tale-two-chickens">studies have shown</a>
that many of the decisions we make are actually rationalized after the fact.)</p>

<p>Neither does the possibility of indeterminism offer any refuge for free will,
claims Harris. I think he is being accurate when he states that arguing against
determinism is no longer &ldquo;philosophically respectable,&rdquo; but nevertheless there
are some who persist in doing so. In fact, often as a way to salvage traditional
notions of free will, &ldquo;some scientists and philosophers hope that chance or
quantum uncertainty can make room for [it].&rdquo; This argument doesn&rsquo;t stand up to
much scrutiny, though, and Harris dispatches it succinctly, observing that
&ldquo;[c]hance occurrences are by definition ones for which I can claim no
responsibility. And if certain of my behaviors are truly the result of chance,
they should be surprising <em>even to me</em>. How would neurological ambushes of this
kind make me free?&rdquo;</p>

<p>Harris reserves a couple chapters at the end of the book to discuss the
practical consequences of giving up one&rsquo;s belief in free will. I found these
chapters somewhat perfunctory and unconvincing. In fairness, they are tangential
to the actual purpose of the book, but given how deeply the assumption of free
will is rooted in human psychology and society, I would have liked to see a more
thorough discussion here. Moreover, I think Harris could have made room for that
by eschewing some of his examples of how we <em>feel</em> free but really aren&rsquo;t, many
of which are reducible to the same observations and therefore feel repetitive
despite the book&rsquo;s short length.</p>

<p>On the impact of disbelief in free will on our behavior, Harris writes:</p>

<blockquote><p>Many people worry that free will is a necessary illusion&mdash;and that
without it we will fail to live creative and fulfilling lives. This concern
isn&rsquo;t entirely unjustified. One study found that having subjects read an
argument against the existence of free will made them more likely to cheat on
a subsequent exam. Another found such subjects to be less helpful and more
aggressive. It is surely conceivable that knowing (or emphasizing) certain
truths about the human mind could have unfortunate psychological and/or
cultural consequences. However, I&rsquo;m not especially worried about degrading
the morality of my readers by publishing this book.</p></blockquote>

<p>(Again, Harris provides citations for the studies he references.) Harris goes on
to justify the last sentence with reference to his personal experience of losing
his sense of free will, stating that it has &ldquo;[increased his] feelings of
compassion and forgiveness, and [diminished his] sense of entitlement to the
fruits of my own good luck.&rdquo; I suppose his experience shows that it is
<em>possible</em> for losing one&rsquo;s belief in free will to have positive (or at least
neutral) psychological consequences, but given that research shows that this is
not the typical result, I don&rsquo;t think that a personal anecdote should be enough
to set us at ease. Of course, it should go without saying that this has no
bearing on the existence or non-existence of free will.</p>

<p>Harris&#8217; discussion of morality is a bit more satisfying. He observes that,
without a belief in free will, retributive justice becomes difficult if not
impossible to justify: &ldquo;Once we recognize that even the most terrifying
predators are, in a very real sense, unlucky to be who they are, the logic of
hating (as opposed to fearing) them begins to unravel.&rdquo; This is eminently
compatible with modern liberal understandings of how justice should operate.
Happily, the logic behind rehabilitation, incarceration for the safety of
society, and punishment as a means of deterrence, remains intact: &ldquo;It may seem
paradoxical to hold people responsible for what happens in their corner of the
universe, but once we break the spell of free will, we can do this precisely to
the degree that it is useful.&rdquo;</p>

<h4>Compatibilism</h4>

<p>Astute readers may have noticed that I mentioned that Harris argues against
comaptibilism, but that thus far I have neglected to actually address those
arguments. That is because Harris&#8217; incompatibilist position is both somewhat
complex, and certainly the most controversial part of <em>Free Will</em>, at least
among philosophers.  Indeed, it is Harris&#8217; dismissal of compatibilism that
compelled professional philosopher Dan Dennett to write a
<a href="http://www.samharris.org/blog/item/reflections-on-free-will">criticism</a>
of the book that is, as Harris observed, &ldquo;nearly as long as the book itself.&rdquo;
I&rsquo;m going to refer to both Dennett&rsquo;s criticism and Harris&#8217;
<a href="http://www.samharris.org/blog/item/the-marionettes-lament">response to it</a>
throughout this section, which is unorthodox for a review, but in this case I
think those works make an extremely valuable addendum to the book itself, as
they expose (to a greater degree than the book does) the core of the
disagreement between Dennett&rsquo;s compatibilism and Harris&#8217; incompatibilism. (Where
I quote Harris, it will be from the text of <em>Free Will</em>, unless otherwise
noted.)</p>

<p>&ldquo;Consider what it would actually take to have free will,&rdquo; Harris writes. &ldquo;You
would need to be aware of all the factors that determine your thoughts and
actions, and you would need to have complete control over those factors.&rdquo; Harris
takes this as, I think, basically axiomatic, but compatibilists disagree.
Dennett writes that &ldquo;[s]uch &lsquo;perfect&rsquo; freedom is, of course, an incoherent
idea,&rdquo; which is true, but I think this is actually Harris&#8217; point: this is the
free will that people <em>suppose</em> they have, but when one thinks about the
implications of that belief, it is shown to be nonsensical.</p>

<p>Here we arrive at another disagreement between Dennett and Harris: Dennett
argues that Harris doesn&rsquo;t actually know what people in general think about free
will, and that &ldquo;suitably expressed questionnaires might well prove him wrong.&rdquo;
In fact, he provides a
<a href="http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/summary;jsessionid=E39CD0E070F0F373146843196443CF02?doi=10.1.1.364.2437">study</a>
which he purports does exactly that: polls conducted but <em>Nahmias et al.</em> appear
to show that people with no philosophical background actually do have
compatibilist notions of free will.</p>

<p>In his response to Dennett, Harris disputes the validity of this study, noting
that &ldquo;Nahmias and his coauthors repeatedly worry that their experimental
subjects didn&rsquo;t really understand the implications of determinism&mdash;and on
my reading, they had good reason to be concerned. &hellip; More than anything, this
research suggests that people find the idea of libertarian free will so
intuitively compelling that it is very difficult to get them to think clearly
about determinism.&rdquo; I have to say that I am in agreement with Harris here.
Having read the paper, it is not at all clear to me that <em>Nahmias et al</em>
accurately assessed their subjects&#8217; compatibilist or incompatibilist
beliefs. They write:</p>

<blockquote><p>Despite our efforts to induce participants to make their judgments based on a
conditional acceptance of the scenario, it is likely that some did not do so,
as evidenced by those who missed the manipulation check on the back of the
surveys, which tested whether they recognized the deterministic nature of the
scenario. Some of these participants may have even been expressing
incompatibilist intuitions, e.g., by asserting that Jeremy acts of his own
free will and then (mis)responding that the scenario therefore could <em>not</em>
have been describing a fully deterministic situation.</p></blockquote>

<p>I agree with Harris that this is a very valid concern, and I&rsquo;m not convinced
that the &ldquo;manipulation check&rdquo; (which isn&rsquo;t described in much detail) would have
been sufficient to account for it. <em>Nahmias et al</em> note that &ldquo;many&rdquo; participants
found the deterministic scenarios they used &ldquo;implausible or impossible,&rdquo; and
that in one case, &ldquo;almost all participants&rdquo; believed the scenario was
impossible. While participants&#8217; stated reasons for this belief varied, it seems
entirely plausible to me, and perhaps even likely, that a significant number of
participants could not effectively reason about the situations being presented
because of strong attachments to beliefs that contradict the scenarios&#8217;
premises.</p>

<p>In any case, Dennett argues that even if people do in fact have a natural
tendency towards libertarian incompatibilism (i.e. they believe in free will but
do not believe that it is compatible with determinism, and, perhaps
consequently, disbelieve determinism), this might just show &ldquo;that most people
are suffering from a sort of illusion that could be replaced by wisdom.&rdquo; He
seems to believe that the illusion in this &ldquo;folk conception of free will&rdquo; is
based on Cartesian dualism, and that the goal of compatibilism is to correct
replace this &ldquo;nonsense&rdquo; with something more &ldquo;scientifically sound.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Dennett wonders why Harris objects to this project and suggests that Harris is
arguing for Cartesian dualism, but this is a misconstrual: Harris is simply
drawing a distinction between what we consciously experience and all of the
unconscious processes our brains are engaged in at every moment, of which we
have no (subjective) knowledge. This is an important distinction, because
Dennett&rsquo;s compatibilist view of free will is predicated on the fact that &ldquo;we are
coterminous with everything that goes on inside our bodies, whether we are
conscious of it or not&rdquo; (Harris&#8217; words).  But although this is true, our
subjective, conscious experiences <em>are</em> actually only proxies for the underlying
neural states in our brains; one simply does not have conscious access to the
totality of his or her being. This is not simply a misconception that can be
corrected: it does seem to be, as Harris argues, a &ldquo;psychological fact,&rdquo; and I
would argue that it is probably also a <em>biological</em> fact. I am sure this is not
what Dennett hopes to replace with compatibilism, but I find myself confused
about the nature of the misunderstanding he feels he can correct.</p>

<p>I am reluctant to dismiss Dennett&rsquo;s arguments outright without first reading his
own books on the subject, but intuitively I find myself agreeing with Harris
that compatibilism seems like a cop out. I have spent quite some time trying to
get at the root of this intuitive feeling, and I&rsquo;ve found it difficult to do so
even with reference to Harris&#8217; arguments, which makes me suspicious of its
validity. But I think this paragraph by Dennett at least gets <em>close</em> to the
core of my skepticism about compatibilism:</p>

<blockquote><p>Contrast your competence at this moment [of deciding which card to play in
bridge] with the &ldquo;competence&rdquo; of a robotic bridge-playing doll that always
plays its highest card in the suit, no matter what the circumstances.  It
wasn&rsquo;t free to choose the six, because it would play the ace whatever the
circumstances were whereas if it occurred to you to play the six, you could do
it, depending on the circumstances. Freedom involves the ability to have one&rsquo;s
choices influenced by changes in the world that matter under the
circumstances.  Not a perfect ability, but a reliable ability. If you are such
a terrible bridge player that you can never see the virtue in ducking a trick,
playing less than the highest card in your hand, then your free will at the
bridge table is seriously abridged: you are missing the opportunities that
make bridge an interesting game. If determinism is true, are these real
opportunities?  Yes, as real as an opportunity could be: thanks to your
perceptual apparatus, your memory, and the well-lit environment, you are
caused/determined to evaluate the situation as one that calls for playing the
six, and you play the six.</p></blockquote>

<p>If we instead contrast a human chess player with a computer such as
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deep_Blue_(chess_computer)">Deep Blue</a>,
we see that the latter has all of the faculties that Dennett claims give a
person free will: &ldquo;perceptual apparatus,&rdquo; memory, etc. Granted, the human player
could purposefully make a bad move, or quit the game, which the computer is not
free to do given its programming. But its programming could easily be changed to
permit those options as well. The point is that the computer behaves in a
determined manner according to the combination of its algorithm and the inputs
to that algorithm. Dennett seems to admit that we humans do exactly the same, if
with a more complex algorithm and broader range of inputs, but claims that this
is freedom nevertheless. But this does not seem to me to be a meaningful use of
the word <em>freedom</em>, and I think Harris is correct that it is not the sort of
freedom that most people suppose they have.</p>

<h4>Conclusion</h4>

<p>Despite the length at which I&rsquo;ve discussed <em>Free Will</em>, there is much that I did
not cover. If you found this discussion even moderately interesting, then you&rsquo;ll
certainly enjoy the book, and I do recommend reading both Dennett&rsquo;s criticism
and Harris&#8217; response to it as well. Philosophical concepts can be extremely
difficult to grapple with, and reading about them second-hand is rarely
beneficial to understanding.</p>

<p>I really enjoyed reading <em>Free Will</em>, and I found myself agreeing with pretty
much all of it, but I hesitate to call it <em>convincing</em>: I was already skeptical
of the idea of free will given our scientific understanding of determinism, so I
really didn&rsquo;t need much persuasion. For those who feel a deep sense of
attachment to the idea of free will, I am not sure Harris&#8217; arguments will be
sufficient to convince you otherwise.  As the debate between Dennett and Harris
demonstrates, the concept itself can be so nebulous as to make it difficult to
even discuss. This may also prove an obstacle for those who lack exposure to
philosophical reasoning, as the arguments can sometimes seem to devolve into
semantic disputes. Conversely, those with a <em>significant</em> philosophical
background may find <em>Free Will</em> uninteresting as they&rsquo;re likely to have read
similar arguments before. For everyone else, though, it comes highly
recommended: this is the rare sort of book that could really have a profound
impact on a person, and it can be read in a sitting, so there&rsquo;s really not much
to lose.</p>

<p>Well, except your sense of autonomy, I suppose.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      




<title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review: Dataclysm]]></title>
<link href="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2014/10/08/dataclysm-who-we-are-when-we-think-no-ones-looking/"/>
<updated>2014-10-08T22:51:00-07:00</updated>
<id>http://blog.mlindgren.ca/entry/2014/10/08/dataclysm-who-we-are-when-we-think-no-ones-looking</id>

      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you&rsquo;ve ever read OkCupid&rsquo;s popular <a href="http://blog.okcupid.com/">OkTrends</a> blog,
you&rsquo;re already familiar with the work of Christian Rudder. As OkCupid&rsquo;s resident
mathematician and one of its founders, he has been writing for years about
statistical trends related to dating and attraction, leveraging OkCupid&rsquo;s
vast database of traits about, and interactions between, its millions and millions
of users. OkTrends produced numerous interesting and surprising results, and it
developed a significant following before going quiet for the better part of
three years beginning in 2011.</p>

<p>Now, Rudder is back with
<a href="http://dataclysm.org/"><em>Dataclysm: Who We Are When We Think No One&rsquo;s Looking</em></a>,
which expands on OkTrends by drawing from a wider variety of sources (including
Facebook, Google, and Twitter, in addition to OkCupid and other dating sites)
and discussing a more diverse set of topics.  Organized into three themed
sections which focus on, respectively, unity, division, and individuality, the
book explores what data can tell us about gender, sexuality, race, identity,
community, and other sociopolitical questions.  The discussion is consistently
balanced and neutral, which is important when dealing with such potentially
charged subjects, but Rudder also manages to inject enough of his personality
and characteristic style to keep the book enjoyable throughout.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Indeed, the OkTrends blog was popular not only for the fascinating observations
it produced, but also for Rudder&rsquo;s accessible and entertaining writing style,
and he continues this to great effect in Dataclysm. No mathematical or
statistical knowledge whatsoever is required to understand the topics discussed
in the book; data are presented in the form of simple graphs and explained using
plain English with a minimum of jargon.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, this focus on accessibility also gives rise to my biggest
criticism of the book: on the spectrum of &ldquo;pop science&rdquo; writing, <em>Dataclysm</em> is
decidedly more pop than science. In and of itself, that isn&rsquo;t a problem per se,
but in many instances I felt that a more methodical approach could have led to a
broader and more productive discussion.  Rudder is not nearly thorough enough in
describing the methodology by which he arrived at his conclusions, nor in
presenting (or at least making available) salient facts about the data he used,
nor in exploring alternative hypotheses.</p>

<p>For example, consider the following graph of the &ldquo;perception of male vs. female
attractiveness&rdquo; from the introduction. On the x-axis is the average of all
ratings (on a 1-5 star scale) received by a user, and on the y-axis is the
percentage of all users that received that average rating:</p>

<div style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;">
<img src="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/images/men_women_attractiveness.png" alt="Attractiveness of women as
rated by men and vice versa"/><br />
<small>Copyright 2014 Christian Rudder. Used under Fair Use.</small>
</div>


<p><br /></p>

<p>Rudder explains:</p>

<blockquote><p>Our real-world data [of women&rsquo;s attractiveness as rated by men] diverges only
slightly (6 percent) from this formulaic ideal [of a symmetric beta
distribution] &hellip; it implies that the individual men who did the scoring are
likewise predictable, centered, and above all, unbiased&hellip; It&rsquo;s practically
common sense that men should have unrealistic expectations of women&rsquo;s looks,
and yet here we see it&rsquo;s just not true.</p>

<p>The red chart [of men&rsquo;s attractiveness as rated by women] is cenetered barely
a quarter of the way up the scale; only one in six guys is &ldquo;above average&rdquo; in
an absolute sense&hellip; [as an analogy,] translate this plot to IQ, and you have
a world where women think 58% of men are brain damaged.</p></blockquote>

<p>This is certainly interesting data in its own right, but I don&rsquo;t think Rudder
goes far enough in exploring what it means or why it might be the case. By
comparing against a similar random sample from a social network, he determines
that it is <em>not</em> because men on OkCupid are unusually ugly&mdash;this pattern
persists beyond dating sites. His hypothesis is simply that &ldquo;men and women
perform a different sexual calculus,&rdquo; and, quoting <em>Harper&rsquo;s Magazine</em>, he notes
that &ldquo;women are inclinded to regret the sex they had, and men the sex they
didn&rsquo;t.&rdquo;</p>

<p>This is certainly a plausible explanation, and it&rsquo;s intuitively appealing, but
it also seems like a bit of a cop out based stereotypical beliefs about gender
differences. I&rsquo;d like to see data about how straight men and women rate the
attractiveness of people of their own gender&mdash;although not directly
analogous since it would be divorced from sexual desire, I suspect that the
results might raise questions about Rudder&rsquo;s hypothesis here.</p>

<p>In the interest of fairness, I must restate that his discussion takes place in
the book&rsquo;s introduction, so it&rsquo;s not representative of the length at which other
findings in the book are discussed. Most likely, it&rsquo;s just meant to pique the
reader&rsquo;s interest and serve as an example of the kind of data the book will
examine. Nevertheless, similar issues persist in later chapters of the book.
Consider this map of responses to the question &ldquo;Should flag burning be illegal?&rdquo;
among OkCupid users:</p>

<div style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;">
<img src="http://blog.mlindgren.ca/images/dataclysm_flag_burning.png" alt="Map of answers to the
question: Should flag burning be illegal?"/><br />
<small>Copyright 2014 Christian Rudder. Used under Fair Use.</small>
</div>


<p><br /></p>

<p>Rudder claims that this map demonstrates that &ldquo;this is truly a nation defined by
its principles, or, as you can see, <em>two</em> nations: Urban and Rural.&rdquo; But to my
eyes, the colors overlap too much to make a meaningful distinction; this
really just looks like a population map. What&rsquo;s more, it appears to include
Canadian responses even though I can only assume that Rudder is referring the US
when he writes &ldquo;<em>a</em> nation,&rdquo; singular. And again, there is no discussion of
important methodological questions or possible confounding factors, such as
whether OkCupid&rsquo;s user base is disproportionately urban (which doesn&rsquo;t seem
unlikely to me), and whether or not that was corrected for if so.</p>

<p>Rudder anticipates criticism of his decision to eschew &ldquo;statistical esoterica,&rdquo;
and defends it as follows:</p>

<blockquote><p>I don&rsquo;t mention confidence intervals, sample sizes, p values, and similar
devices in <em>Dataclysm</em> because the book is above all a popularization of data
and data science&hellip; But like the spars and crossbeams of a house, the rigor is
no less present for being unseen. Many of the findings of the book are drawn
from academic, peer-reviewed sources. I applied the same standards to the
research I did myself&hellip;</p></blockquote>

<p>I fully accept that there is a place for and a value to &ldquo;popularization&rdquo; of
scientific fields, and that it&rsquo;s sensible to exclude complex statistical
measures which would be meaningless to most readers&hellip; <em>from the main body of
the text</em>. But I don&rsquo;t see why Rudder didn&rsquo;t even see fit to include these as
footnotes or endnotes, which the book does have. And with respect to the
academic research used, Rudder relegates all of his citations to endnotes, which
usually link back to the text referring to them, but are not linked to <em>from</em>
that text, which can make it very hard to match up specific statements with the
studies supporting them.</p>

<p>All of this criticism notwithstanding, I really enjoyed reading <em>Dataclysm</em>, and
I would heartily recommend it to anyone interested in gaining insight into the
social and political identities of (primarily American) Internet users. Anyone
interested in the burgeoning field of data science would also likely enjoy this
book. It&rsquo;s just worth noting that some of Rudder&rsquo;s conclusions should be taken
with a healthy dose of skepticism until they can be replicated with rigor that
<em>is</em> seen.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
</feed>

